<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vsurers plea answered In a sermon preached at Southampton the 18. day of Iuly, being Thursday, and their lecture day, 1633. By Roger Turner Mr. of Arts, and minister of Gods Word neere Southampton.</title>
            <author>Turner, Roger, b. 1603.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14043</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109442</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845089</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845089</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9966</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14043)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9966)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1223:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vsurers plea answered In a sermon preached at Southampton the 18. day of Iuly, being Thursday, and their lecture day, 1633. By Roger Turner Mr. of Arts, and minister of Gods Word neere Southampton.</title>
                  <author>Turner, Roger, b. 1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E[lizabeth] P[urslowe] for Robert Bostocke, and are to be sould at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Kings head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Matthew XXV, 27.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Usury --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9966:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VSVRERS PLEA ANSWERED.</p>
            <p>In a Sermon preached at <hi>Southampton</hi> the 18. day of <hi>Iuly,</hi> being Thurſday, and their Lecture day, 1633.</p>
            <p>By ROGER TVRNER M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of Arts, and Miniſter of Gods Word neere SOVTHAMPTON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>AVG. in Pſal. 36. Serm. 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Qui prohibit te eſſe foeneratorum ille jubet te eſſe foeneratorem.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>E. P.</hi> for <hi>Robert Boſtocke,</hi> and are to be ſould at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Kings head, 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9966:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9966:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull the Maior, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Burgeſſes, and the reſt of that ancient and famous Corporation of Southampton, <hi>the Author wiſheth</hi> the bleſſings of this life and of a better.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLEMEN,</hi> here is that preſented to your eyes, which not long ſince ſounded in your eares; that common Apologie for being men in print, (the importunity of friends) cannot be altogether mine, for ſome whom this may moſt concerne, will leaſt deſire it; but when I remember that ancient ſaying of <hi>Lucian,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Encomien pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that the ſmoake of a mans owne country is better than the fire of another; I doubt not but that theſe my tender labours (which are but ſmoaky vapours of ignorance, compared to the enlightning fire of others knowledge, ſuch as daily you heare) ſhall finde an eaſier paſſage into your acceptance, becauſe here I had my firſt being where you all have your happy dwelling. 'Twas once farre from my meaning to have expoſed my ſelfe to the paraphraſe of this cenſorious age, but rather to have hid this weak conception, never to have
<pb facs="tcp:9966:3"/>come to the birth: but when it would no longer endure to be impriſoned in the womb, but violently breake forth; I thought (being my first borne) to deale cautelouſly with it, though not with the Aegyptians cruelly to murther it; yet with <hi>Moſes</hi> his parents charitably to hide it for my owne private uſe, it might have had the hap to have been ſtill-borne, but it hath cried, and ſome that then heard it, have ſince deſired to heare it ſpeake, thinking it may live and doe ſome good, and although it ſpeake ſomewhat bitterly, and bite ſo cloſe (which perhaps ſome may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh) yet it bites nothing but ſinne, I ſee no reaſon why we ſhould ſpare the leaſt ſinne, ſince for it the world was drowned to puniſh it, the Law given to prevent it, the Sonne of the moſt high dyed to ſatisfie for it, and the world ſhall againe be deſtroyed to finiſh it, much leſse a ſinne of this nature, ſo hainous, ſo deteſtable. For the matter hereof I have imitated, not the ſpider, but the Bee, the ſpiders web is not the more commendable becauſe it is woven out of its owne bowels, nor the Bees honey leſſe uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and pleaſant becauſe it is gathered from ſeverall flowers, what ever it be 'twas yours first in the intention and occaſion; now in the protection and nouriſhment: 'tis not ſo farre put forth to nurſe, but that the parents ſhall quickly ſee the good uſage of it, if it thrive in your kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, you have crowned the deſires and endeavours of him who is at</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſervice in Chriſt, and for his truth, ROGER TVRNER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9966:3"/>
            <head>THE VSVRERS PLEA ANSWERED.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATH. 25.27.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Thou oughteſt therefore to have put my money to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changers, that when J had come, J might have had my owne with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words at the firſt view may ſeeme to countenance a ſinne, too frequently pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in theſe gold-thirſty dayes; I meane that biting ſinne of Vſury, grown now to a profeſſion; but the Text being parabolicall, cannot be a ſufficient foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, whereon to raiſe an argument to prove the lawfulneſſe thereof: for it is an ancient ſaying in the Schooles, that <hi>Scriptura parabolica non eſt argumentativa:</hi> &amp; beſides,<note place="margin">22. <hi>q.</hi> 78. <hi>art.</hi> 1.1. <hi>m.</hi>
               </note> this Vſury here in the Text is taken metaphorically (as <hi>Aquinas</hi> obſerves) for ſpirituall thriftineſſe, and the increaſe of thoſe ſpirituall gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which God beſtowes upon us, willing us to profit, gaine, and goe forward in them; which tends to our advantage, not unto his; this will more eaſily appeare if wee obſerve but the ſcope and drift of this parable, which I will but touch, that ſo it may appeare how farre they are miſtaken, who make this Text a foundation whereon to ground the lawfulneſſe of Vſury.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:9966:4"/>
            <p>The Parable begins thus; The Kingdome of heaven is like unto a man who going into a farre Country called his ſervants and delivered them his goods, to one he gave five tallents, to another two, to a third one, to each man according to his abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, prudence, and faculty to gaine thereby, the firſt that had received five tallents by his induſtry doubled them and gained five more;<note place="margin">Verſe 16.</note> ſo he that had received two, gained likewiſe other two; but he that received one, fearing that if he ſhould have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed his tallent, inſtead of gaine hee might reape ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment or loſſe, hee therefore digs and hides his talent in the earth, thinking that he had done ſufficiently if he reſtored his money whole to his Maſter as he received it.</p>
            <p>After a long ſeaſon, the Maſter of theſe ſervants returnes to call them to account; the firſt that by the well imployment of his five tallents had gained five more, is entertained by his Maſter both with praiſe and reward; ſo likewiſe the ſecond; but the third, when he came to give an account, confeſſeth that he had hid his tallent in the earth, and begins by laying an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation on his Maſter to excuſe himſelfe for ſo doing: I knew (ſaith he to his Maſter) that thou wert an hard man,<note place="margin">Verſe 24.</note> reaping where thou ſowedſt not, and gathering where thou ſtrowedſt not; I was therefore afraid, and went and hid my talent in the earth, behold thou haſt thine own; but his Maſter by way of increpation retorts his owne words, calling him evill and ſlothfull ſervant; ſeeing, ſaith he, thou kneweſt me to be ſuch a one as thou ſaieſt, reaping where I ſowed not, and gathering where I ſtrowed not, thou oughteſt therefore to have given my money to the Exchangers, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now for the explication hereof, by a certaine man here is meant our bleſſed Savior, by going into a far country is meant his departure from earth to heaven, where hee now ſits at the right hand of his Father, till he ſhall returne unto judgement, he called his ſervants, that is, us Chriſtians into his Church, to us be hath delivered his goods <hi>i. e.</hi> gifts and bleſſings both corporall and ſpirituall, for all are the gifts of God, now becauſe God gives not to every man alike, but on ſome he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes greater gifts, on other leſſer: therefore the Maſter is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9966:4"/>here ſaid to give to one ſervant five tallents, to another two, to a third one, yet all theſe tallents, <hi>i. e.</hi> theſe gifts and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings are beſtowed on us, not that they ſhould be idle, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to advantage and profit; now they are ſaid to gaine by their tallent who religiouſly imploy thoſe gifts of God, as the underſtanding, will, memory, the faculties of ſoule and body, arts, ſciences, and all vertues, and ſo are every day made richer in good workes, and they are compared to the evill and ſlothfull ſervant, who having received many great and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar gifts from God, doe as it were fold them up in a Napkin, bury them in the earth, and ſuffer them to ruſt for want of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, neither benefiting themſelves nor profitting their neighbours; for in the interpretation of S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> he is ſaid to hide and bury his tallent in the earth, who ſavouring of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but earthly things, gives himſelfe over to the pleaſures of this life, neglects the Commandements of God, and choaks the good feed of faith by the thorny cares of this world. This part of the parable then is interpreted of all thoſe gifts in generall, which man receives from God, whether naturall or ſupernaturall, all being beſtowed that they may be improved in ſpirituall thriftineſſe, in the workes of piety and holineſſe, and it agrees to all Chriſtians in generall, but more eſpecially (in the opinion of <hi>Marlorat</hi> and others) to the Miniſters and Paſtours of the Church.</p>
            <p>Concerning the tallent, there are diverſe interpretations thereof, ſome by the five tallents, underſtand the gift of the five ſenſes, by the two tallents knowledge and memory; by one, reaſon whereby men are diſtinguiſht from beaſts; others by the tallent underſtand the Word of God heard and taught; others the gift of faith; others the gift of teaching; or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gift or faculty whatſoever, whereby a man may doe good unto his Neighbour, whether by authority to protect him, or by riches to helpe him, or by learning and wiſdome to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct him, or by any other meanes whereby thou maiſt helpe or profit thy brother. But I haſten to the Text.</p>
            <p>Which is nothing elſe but an Exprobration of the ſlothfull ſervant, for not imploying his tallent as the two former had
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9966:5"/>done: and this rebuke or checke is drawne from the cuſtome of men in theſe dayes who were wont to let out their money upon Vſury; the word in the originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Table<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, they were called <hi>Campſores</hi> or <hi>Foeneratores</hi> Exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, men that did either exchange great ſummes of money and ſo gained thereby, or elſe they were ſuch as were wont to borrow money upon Vſury; for ſuch kind of men, wanting oftentimes great ſummes of money (as Merchants are wont to doe) were wont to take upon uſe, and afterward pay it againe with ſome profit to the lender; now this kind of gaine was without danger in reſpect of the principall. Therefore the Maſter ſaith to the evill and ſlothfull ſervant, thou oughteſt to have given my mony to the Exchangers, where there might have beene gaine without danger. Now becauſe our Saviour by drawing a ſimilitude, frames a compariſon from the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of thoſe times. Shall any man therefore make this Text a plea to juſtifie him in the practiſe of Vſury?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 16.10.</note> as well may we prove the lawfulneſſe of injuſtice from that Parable of the theeviſh Steward; or of theft, becauſe it is ſaid, that Chriſt ſhall come like a theefe in the night;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.2.</note> or of heatheniſh Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picke-games, in comparing the practiſe of Chriſtians to thoſe rates;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24. <hi>Math.</hi> 11.17.</note> or of dancing from that parabolicall ſpeech, <hi>Wee have piped unto you, and yee have not danced:</hi> But becauſe this Text hath been urged by ſome to prove the lawfulneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that I have ſo oportunely met with this ſinne ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently practiſed, ſo ſeldome preacht againſt; nay, ſome that ſhould tell <hi>Iudah</hi> of this fault, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> of this tranſgreſſion, are ſuch as the Prophet <hi>Eſaiah</hi> ſpeakes of,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56.11.</note> where the Prophet is very bitter, men looking after their owne wayes, every one for his owne advantage, and for his owne purpoſe, practiſers hereof themſelves. I ſhall not goe farre beyond the limits of my Text, if I a little proſecute this ſinne, and yet I muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a prejudicate opinion, I come not like <hi>Aeſops</hi> Foxe, that having no tayle, would needs perſwade all the reſt to cut off theirs: or had I beene bitten, I would not have come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſnarle, the ſinne is all I ayme at, which I intend to purſue.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:9966:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>'Twas the ſaying of a merry man, that in Chriſtendome,<note place="margin">Heyſin Geogr. p. <hi>222.</hi>
               </note> there were neither Schollers enough, Gentlemen enough, nor Iewes enough, and when anſwer was made that of all theſe there were rather too great a plenty than any ſcarcity at all, he replyed, that if there were Schollers enough, there would not be ſo many double and treble beneficed men as there are; if Gentlemen enough, ſo many peaſants would not be ranked amongſt the Gentry; and if Iewes enough, ſo many Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans would not profeſſe Vſury, a ſinne which the Chriſtians firſt learned of the Iewes; and what a ſhame is it that they ſhould now be thought to equall, if not exceed their teachers. But before we cenſure this ſinne, let us firſt know what it is: the deſcription of it is this, <hi>Pastum ex mutuo lucrum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wilſ. Dist.</note> a gaine exacted by covenant, above the principall onely, in lieu and recompence of the lending. There are five things belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to Vſury as neceſſary: Firſt, a principall, as wares, or ſummes of money; Secondly, lending; thirdly, gaine; fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a chiefe purpoſe by lending to increaſe the ſtocke; and laſtly, a covenant for that end, as the very deſire and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of gaine, for lending onely is mentall and intentionall Vſury, ſo the impoſing, or by covenant afore-hand agreeing for increaſe above the principall is actuall Vſury, which is cleane oppoſite unto Gods Word, and may very fitly bee termed biting lucre, ſo the Hebrewes termes it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which comes from the root <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies to bite, and 'tis no ordinary biting, but 'tis uſually taken for the biting of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, ſo the word is uſed<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.9.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> when the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent had bitten a man, then hee looked to the Serpent of braſſe and lived; now this kind of Vſury, poſitive Lawes doe not onely reſtraine but not allow, and the Law of God doth every where condeme, in the 22 of <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.36, 37. the words are perſpicuous and plaine to every mans capacity. <hi>Jf thou lend money to my people that is the poore amongſt you, thou ſhalt not be as a Vſurer unto him, thou ſhalt not oppreſſe him with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury;</hi> yet covetouſneſſe here <hi>Nodum in hoc ſcir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po quaeſivit</hi> hath found out a two-fold evaſion to ſhunne this precept, the firſt exception is verball drawne from the <hi>etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:9966:6"/>of the word; the other is perſonall from the expreſſe mention of the poore, here (ſay ſome) Vſury is forbidden, but the word there uſed is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which (as you now heard) is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from a word which ſignifies to bite, ſo that if it bee not uncivill Vſury, if it be toothleſſe, if it be not biting Vſury, 'tis no breach of this precept, but firſt tis to be obſerved, that it is a true and an ancient ſaying in the Schooles,<note place="margin">Biſhop Andr. de Vſura theolog. determ.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the derivation of words is but a falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and not alwayes to be truſted; and againe, this anſwer will not ſuffice, for there is no Vſury but bites more or leſſe, ſome like the morning Wolfe greedy of his prey, faſtens the teeth more deepely, and that which is but moderated or qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified (as men thinke) perhaps, five, ſixe, or ſeven in the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred; yet what is this, but as it is in the Greeke proverbe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſhave to the very skin; and like the Dog, flee to draw ſome blood: ſo that although all kind of Vſury bite not alike, yet there is no Vſury at all that is toothleſſe: Againe, this anſwer overthrowes the very ground of the Law which bids us to love our Neighbour as our ſelves; 'tis but phariſaicall to ſay, ſo it bee not biting Vſury it matters not, this is ſpoken like a goood Chriſtian, Let mee lend to my brother, ſo I may profit him, ſo I may doe him good there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</p>
            <p>Againe, in <hi>Exodus</hi> 22. and <hi>Leviticus</hi> 25. there is expreſſe mention made of the poore; therefore (ſay ſome) ſo long as we put not our money to uſe to poore men the matter is ſafe enough, but this is eaſily anſwered, that although theſe two places make mention of the poore, yet in the 23. of <hi>Deut.</hi> 19. there is an abſolute law without any relation at all to the poore man, thou ſhalt not give to Vſury to thy Brother, uſury of money, uſury of meale, uſury of any thing that is put to uſury; and whereas it is ſaid in the verſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, unto a ſtranger thou maiſt lend upon Vſury; this was permitted for a time, not as lawfull, but for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding of a greater miſchiefe, and for the hardneſſe of their hearts, as our Saviour ſpeakes of their other pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 19.8.</note> but wee that live in the glorious Sunne-ſhine of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9966:6"/>the Goſpel, ought to account every man our Neighbour and our Brother.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, becauſe the Law forbids taking Vſury of the poore man, doth it therefore permit taking Vſury of the rich? this can neither bee good conſequence nor good Divinity, let mee paralel this place with ſome other places of Scripture;<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.22.</note> it ſaid yee ſhall not trouble any widdow or fatherleſſe child, doth it therefore follow that it is lawfull to wrong him that hath a father, or her that hath a husband?<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.18.</note> The Law ſayes, Curſed is he that maketh the blind goe out of his way, doth it therefore permit not to ſhew the way to him that can ſee?<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.14.</note> The Law provides that the hired ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant if hee be needy and poore ſhall not bee oppreſſed, but have his wages paid him; ſhall we therefore conclude, that if hee be not needy and poore, hee ſhall be deprived thereof? But to come a little neerer I would gladly know the reaſon, ſeeing it is unlawfull to lend money upon uſury to the poore, why ſhould it be lawfull to the rich? is it becauſe his bagges are fuller, he may better ſpare it without prejudice or detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? and is not this to plead the caſe of the Theefe, may not the ſame reaſon ſerve for the Theefe as for the Vſurer, the Theefe may ſay thus with himſelfe, this is a poore man and to be pittied, but that's a rich, a well monyed-man, I will rob him, becauſe he can ſpare it, he can want it without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment or wrong unto his eſtate; but we all know that be a man poore or be he rich, theft is utterly unlawfull; ſo that here Vſury is made no leſſe than a kinde of robberry, and as one tearmes it, <hi>Terreſtris piratica,</hi> a kinde of land-pyracy: So then you ſee that neither the word, neither in the Text, nor yet the expreſſe mention of the poore hinders, but that this precept is univerſall, and that all kind of Vſury, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther civill or uncivill, whether exacted from thoſe of the loweſt condition, or from the richer ſort of men, but is here condemned as unlawfull.</p>
            <p>I will urge this precept a little further. In the Law there are three things the thing forbidden, the cenſure, and the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty; the thing forbidden you have already heard, the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9966:7"/>followes; that is, how this ſinne of Vſury hath beene thought on, and amongſt what ſinnes it hath beene ranked in former ages, and if you reade the Scriptures (which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies wont to admire <hi>Saul</hi> amongſt the Prophets) you ſhall finde a very ſevere and heavy taxation of this ſinne, read but<note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. <hi>18.8.</hi> Baſill.</note> where you ſhall find this ſinne to uſe the words of a Father <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the holy Prophet reckons it in the very midſt of moſt abominable ſinnes, upon the committing of one of which, death followes, as verſ. 13. or hath given forth upon uſury, or hath taken increaſe ſhall he live? and 'tis anſwered in the very next words, Hee ſhall not live, hee ſhall dye the death, and his blood ſhall bee upon him. The penalty is next, and that is two-fold, in this life, and that which is to come: Firſt, in this life reade<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov</hi> 28.8.</note> He that increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his riches by Vſury and intereſt, gathereth them for him that will be mereifull to the poore; where this transferring of ſuch riches to uncertaine heires is an argument of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt poſſeſſion, and therefore unjuſtly poſſeſſed, becauſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly gained: Secondly, in the life to come, and that is the curſe of God. Out of the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.5.</note> Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> frames this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, if he be bleſſed that hath not given his money upon Vſury, then doubtleſſe he is curſed that hath. Now from the Law it ſelfe I proceed to the intent and purpoſe of it: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth very aptly explaine that generall rule and true meaning of all lawfull contracts <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.14.</note> that there may be equality (ſaith he) which was by the very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens themſelves called the fountaine of Iuſtice; this equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is of two ſorts, either internall of the minde, or elſe in things themſelves externally covenanted for: That equality or proportion of minde our Saviour (the beſt interpreter of his Fathers will) hath placed in this that whatſoever wee would that men ſhould doe unto us, even ſo alſo ſhould wee doe unto them<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12.</note>. Now marke, there is none (I preſume) that deſires to have the yoke of Vſury laid on his necke, no not ſo much as toothleſſe Vſury (as they tearme it) but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther none than any at all. Let a man then deale thus with his Brother, let our Saviours rule flouriſh, let Vſury periſh;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9966:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>and as for things themſelves, if we looke to the covenant for loane, there is no equity or equality at all, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. Fent. de Vſura. </seg>
               </label> for the borrower is bound to make good the principall, and to pay the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe for the uſe or the ſame principall for the time it is lent: I demand then during the time of loane, whoſe is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, thine or the borrowers? it was thine before thou lentſt it, and ſhall be thine at the day of payment, but during the time of loane it is the borrowers, for thou haſt by covenant paſſed over both uſe and property unto him, ſo that during that time hee is the owner of it, and if it periſheth, it peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth to the borrower as to the right owner for that time; I aske then by what right canſt thou covenant to receive hire for the uſe of that which is none of thine, during the time it is not thine. If a man let a houſe or land, he may covenant to receive hire, becauſe he hath paſſed over the uſe onely, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the property to himſelfe, therefore if a man make waſte upon ſuch land, the owner may juſtly complaine, becauſe the property is ſtill his; but it is not ſo in money, why then ſhould a man covenant for hire for the uſe of that wherein he hath no right or property; therefore 'tis an unequall bargain the borrower hath the uſe onely of thy principall and payeth for the uſe which alone is his, why then ſhould he beare the perill of thy principall, which is none of his? This is a nice quiddity or Schoole-tricke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.15.</note> but the equity of Gods owne Law, the borrower ſhall not make it good, for if it be a hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thing it came for the hire, it is added, if the owner there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſtand by (to wit) that it appeare to periſh, or by hurt, not by any default of the borower, ſo admit that money could by Vſurers be made a hired thing, yet the equity of Gods Law binds that if it appeare to miſcarry without the fault of the owner, the borrower ſhall not make it good, becauſe it came for hire. So you ſee here is no equity, the Vſurer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives great gaine without labour, cleere gaine without coſt, certaine gaine without perill, out of the induſtry, the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the meere uncertainties of the borrower, a cleanely Alchymiſt that can extract much ſilver and waſt nothing in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9966:8"/>ſmoake, theſe are the Kine of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> that feede upon the Commons.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 4.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As Nature teacheth men to doe that which is ſeemly, kind, and naturall, ſo Religion teacheth Chriſtians in all their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, to depend upon Gods providence, and expect a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from heaven; ſo it ought to be, and ſo it is in all profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions except Vſury, <hi>Nullum de Deo hominum genus pejus ſentiunt quam Daniſtarum,</hi> of all ſort of men, the Vſurer thinkes worſt of God, and will leaſt truſt him, bee it faire or foule, hee will bee ſure of his mony. The Husbandman lookes up to the clouds, and prayes for ſeaſonable weather; the Merchant obſerves the wind, and prayes God to deliver him from tempeſt and wracke; the Trades-man wiſheth the people may have money that he may vent his wares at a reaſonable rate, and live in ſome good faſhion; the labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring man prayes for worke and health, that hee may be able to get a poore living by the ſweat of his browes; onely the Mony-monger hath leaſt need of all other men to ſay his prayers, bee it wet or dry, bee it tempeſt or calme, let the wind blow Eaſt, Weſt, North, or South; be he well, or bee he ſicke, be hee gowty or lame, or ſound of body, let him be what he will, or doe what he liſt, he ſhall bee ſure of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, for time onely workes for him; all the dayes in the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manacke are ſet aworke to worke out his gaine; nay the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath ſhall not be omitted, the red letter is as good for his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as the blacke, to helpe make up the number of daies, of weekes, of moneths, ſo the time goes out, and his money comes in, and hee ſeemes not to ſtand in that need of Gods providence as other honeſt men doe, and can wee thinke in conſcience, that God is pleaſed with ſuch a life?</p>
            <p>And thus you ſee in the firſt place, that Vſury is abſolutely condemned from the authority of ſacred Scriptures; and where this oracle vouchſafes to ſpeake, we need no farther authority for confirmation; but unto this may be added a cloud of witneſſes, as firſt the conſent of Churches Eaſt and Weſt, and if wee reverence the judgement of reverend men both for their learning and ſanctimony of life, they ought to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9966:8"/>be a great motive to ſway our judgements herein; all which were ſo farre from moderating or qualifying this practiſe of Vſury, that whenſoever they met with it, they ſharpned their pens, as if their ſpirits were moved and ſtirred in them more than ordinarily.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe the Church aſſembled in Counſells, have flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decreed againſt it; Clergy-men for this ſinne to be degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; the Laity to be excommunicated: all this (I ſuppoſe) is enough to prove Vſury a ſinne. But yet if the light of nature bee able to diſcover the ſame, 'twill aggravate the matter much more; there are Moats which are not diſcerned but in the Sun-ſhine; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> faith<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7.</note> that hee had not knowne that concupiſcence had beene a ſinne, except the law had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted the ſame; and ſuppoſe that Vſury were but as a moat in the eye, yet that were troubleſome, becauſe the eye is tender, as the conſcience of every Chriſtian ought to be, but if the inhabitants of the Regions of darkeneſſe that never ſaw the ſun-ſhine of revealed truth, ſhall notwithſtanding diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne Vſury to be inordinate and vitious, doubtleſſe then 'tis no Moat; beames may be diſcovered by the twi-light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo hath Vſury ever beene held even amongſt the heathens themſelves for a groſſe inormity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plato</hi> in his Lawes, and his Scholer <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks, have forbidden it as unlawfull,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Lib. cap. <hi>7.</hi> polit. Cic. de Off. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Seneca lib. <hi>7.</hi> de Benef.</note> and condemned it as unnaturall; <hi>Cato</hi> makes it twice as bad as theft, and equals it with murder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Quid foenerari? quid hominem occidere?</hi> (<hi>Seneca</hi> in his 7. booke <hi>De Benef.</hi>) <hi>Quid foenus &amp; Kalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darium &amp; Vſura niſi humanae cupiditates extra naturam quaeſita nomina;</hi> he findes a place for it in the Kallender, but not in nature.<note place="margin">Plutarch. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> writes that Vſurers mocke the Philoſophers for that old Principle, <hi>Ex nihilo nihil fit,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they can make ſomething of nothing; and hence hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily it is that the Latines proper tearme for Vſury is <hi>Foenus quaſi foetus pecuniae,</hi> the brood of mony; and in the ſame ſenſe did the Greekes call it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies to breed or bring forth, though ſome would derive <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies deceit or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:9966:9"/>oppreſſion; as if Vſury were not to be miſliked for its owne ſake, unleſſe it were convicted of ſome ſenſible oppreſſion, but the conſent of the Grammarians fetcheth it neerer hand, taking the Nowne from the Verbe, and the primitive ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is birth, next it ſignifies the iſſue it ſelfe, as the firſt-borne is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and according to theſe two ſignifications, ſome have given a double reaſon of this name,<note place="margin">Ambroſe lib. de Tobia cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Graeci appellarunt Vſuras</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>eo quod dolores par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus animae debitoris excitare videantur,</hi> the Grecians call Vſury by a name which ſignifies birth, becauſe it brings the pangs of travell upon the ſoule of the Debtor; a woman in travell doth not ſweat and labour to bring forth with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter anguiſh of mind, than a Debtor compelled to bring home the principall with increaſe. Another<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> makes Month <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the onely fathers; and borrowers, the onely mothers to bring forth this unnaturall brood of Vſury, unnaturall even as the brood of Vipers, which eate thorow the entralls of their mother; ſo doth the borrower bring forth to the Vſurer, to the deſtruction oftentimes of himſelfe and family. And Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayes that mony thus lent,<note place="margin">In quintum Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thei.</note> is like the biting of the Serpent, called <hi>Aſpis,</hi> for he that is ſtung by that Serpent feeleth a kind of pleaſant itch, whereby he falls aſleepe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. Wilſoa de Vſura. </seg>
               </label> and through the pleaſantneſſe of his ſleepe dyes in pleaſure, for then the poiſon by little and little, diſperſeth it ſelfe through ali the parts of the body; ſo after a man hath once taken up mony upon Vſury, and lives pleaſantly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with for a time, at length the Vſury ſo pierceth through his whole eſtate, that neither lands nor livings are able to pay his debts. <hi>Pliny</hi> makes mention of a worme called <hi>Teredos</hi> that breeds in Timber,<note place="margin">Plin. lib. <hi>7.</hi> Nat. Hiſt.</note> which being touched or handled, ſeemes very ſoft, and yet hath ſuch hard teeth, that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes all manner of wood, the Barke, and out ſide remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing intire. Many men now adayes make a faire ſhew with other mens mony thus borrowed, but if every Bird ſhould fetch his feather, would be as naked as <hi>Aeſops</hi> Crow, for when death hewes them downe, their eſtates prove like a hollow tree, no ſound Timber for poſterity to build withall;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9966:9"/>for this worme of Vſury hath gnawed away their ſubſtance: Mony thus taken up is like a new piece put into an old gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which being taken away the rent is made worſe.</p>
            <p>Now he that is a Vſurer, if you aske what hee is, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. Fent. </seg>
               </label> or of what profeſſion, he will not gladly owne that name; mens conſciences are more troubled at the name, than at the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the ſinne: ſome therefore calls him a man that puts out his mony, but this is ambiguous, hee may put it out, as the Lion puts out his claw, and then woe bee to him that comes neere his grate; but moſt commonly, he is tearmed one that lives upon his mony, and this is without all excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for as the Gentlemen lives upon his rents; the poore labourer upon the ſweat of his browes; the Merchant and Tradeſ-man, upon their adventures, skill, and induſtry; the Husband-man and Graſier, upon the increaſe of the earth, and breed of Cattell; ſo the Vſurer lives upon his monies, that yeanes, and foales, and calves to him once in ſix months at fartheſt. What a foole then was <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> to call mony barren, which yeelds a double harveſt, at the leaſt, every yeere, and the former crop makes ſeed-Corne for the next.</p>
            <p>Nature hath eſtabliſhed to all things under the Sunne, a certaine tearme, and pitch, when they ſhall make ſtay of increaſe, and multiplying; the land if it want a jubile, will in time grow heartleſſe; houſes if they be not re-edified, will decay; trees will leave bearing; cattell breeding, when they grow old; mens labours and skill will faile with yeeres, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Vſurers mony doth multiply infinitely, the longer the luſtier, if he can but live he may ſee his monies monies mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; even to an hundred generations; and is not this unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall? Surely it hath but ſmall reſemblance to that naturall increaſe, which the God of nature hath eſtabliſhed, as moſt innocent amongſt men; is it not ſtrange, that men of all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſhould inveigh ſo bitterly againſt this ſinne, it ſeemes 'tis of a moſt devouring nature, as the Poet ſayes<note n="*" place="margin">Lucan.</note> 
               <hi>Hinc Vſura vorax avidum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in pectore foenus,</hi> and brings men to ſtrange extremities,<note place="margin">Ariſtoph. comaed. de nubibus.</note> as it did poore <hi>Strepſiades</hi> (whoſe eſtate was ſhip-wrackt by fraighting with Vſury) that could deviſe no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9966:10"/>better ſhift than to a hire a Witch to pull the Moone out of Heaven, that the Vſurers moneths might never come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.</p>
            <p>If this ſinne then can find no footing, either in Divinity or Nature, how ſhall it ſtand? Divines have excommunicated it out of the Church; Philoſophers have proved it a Monſter in Nature; yet for all this it hath taken deepe root in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, both Heatheniſh and Chriſtian; the ancient Romans, ſeeing the miſchiefe of Vſury, would tollerate but their <hi>Foenus unciarium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacitus lib. <hi>5.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nalium.</note> one in the hundred (as <hi>Cornelius Tacitus</hi> relates) and whoſoever exceeded that, ſhould bee puniſhed foure-fold; whereas by the Law of their twelve Tables, theft was to he puniſhed but two-fold; it ſeemes in thoſe dayes if theeves had been ſcarſe, <hi>Foeneratores bis fures,</hi> a Vſurer was to goe for two: <hi>Mahomet</hi> himſelfe hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned it amongſt the Turkes,<note place="margin">Alcoran Azoar <hi>4.6.11.</hi>
               </note> as is to be ſeene in their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coran, and aſcribes the miſeries of the Iewes to this ſinne of Vſury. So carefull have Governours ever beene amongſt Heathen and Barbarians to ſuppreſſe this Monſter; for what Country hath Vſury ever beene ſuffered in, which in time hath not rued the ſame? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. Andr. de Vſuris. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Cicily</hi> was in great bondage by it, till <hi>Cato</hi> ſet it at liberty; <hi>Sparta</hi> in no leſſe calamity, till <hi>Licurgus</hi> redeemed it; all <hi>Aegypt</hi> ſo plagued with it, that they were glad to make a Law, that none ſhould borrow, unleſſe he laid his Fathers corps to pawne; <hi>Athens</hi> infected with it, till <hi>Agis</hi> his bone-fire of Vſurers bonds had purged that City.</p>
            <p>Meditating upon that plague of Flies, which was the fourth plague which God ſent upon the Egyptians<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.24.</note>. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the nature of theſe, we may not unfitly compare V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers unto them, for as theſe flies did ſucke out the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans blood, by byting and ſtinging, and cauſing of ſmart, ſo theſe men with their, <hi>Noverint Vniverſi,</hi> make a univerſall ruine of many a mans eſtate, and ſo fetch him in ſtill with the condition of the obligation, that at length his condition is wofull, and his very heart breakes with the bitter thought of, <hi>Bee it knowne unto all men:</hi> theſe are curſed flies, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9966:10"/>ſuckers of mens ſap, the drinkers of their blood, the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Flie was nothing like theſe, but it was a great plague of God, ſent to puniſh the ſinnes of men, but withall let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that theſe flies of Egypt had but a time, God ſent them in wrath, and tooke them away in mercy: upon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty, ſome <hi>Moſes</hi> or other, may in time ſtand up, and God may ſend a ſtrong Weſt-wind to ſweep theſe canker wormes away; if <hi>England</hi> were as well cleered of theſe, as it is of Wolves, it would be ſo much the happier.</p>
            <p>What then muſt bee the concluſion of all the premiſſes, Charity, Iuſtice, Piety; Nature her ſelfe, the Lawes of God and of men, all authority, ancient and moderne, joyning their forces againſt the Vſurer, how can be ſtand environed with ſuch a cloud of witneſſes, or juſtifie himſelfe againſt the day of triall? Yet few men there are in theſe dayes that have any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe or touch of conſcience for this ſinne, their conſciences are caute rized as with a hot iron, there is ſuch a thicke skin growne over their hearts, that they will hardly be circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in this point, and this ſenſeleſſe ſtupidity ſeemes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed originally from three principall cauſes; firſt, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall practiſe of Vſury makes every one in particular to thinke that he ſhall ſhift as well as others; now cuſtome and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple though it would not be admitted in Schooles for an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet it workes much upon vulgar underſtandings, for the people being as <hi>Labans</hi> ſheepe, led by the eye, conceive as they fee; ſeeing therefore Vſury ſo much practized of all ſorts, men are thereby without farther conſideration much moved to thinke it lawfull. If it be ſo hainous a ſinne to take Vſury as you make it (ſay ſome) what ſhall become of ſuch and ſuch, who (I am ſure) have as good ſoules to God as I? pray God I have no greater ſinne to anſwer for than this, and then I hope I ſhall do well enough. See the power and efficacy of example, but let none be ſo ſimple as to thinke that the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of any thing ſhould make it lawfull; this is a fearefull temptation to be drawne into ſinne by imitation; 'twas that which turned ſo many legions of Angels into Devils, to ſee the brighter and more glorious Spirits leave their ſtation by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9966:11"/>diſobedience; but did that mitigate Gods wrath toward them of inferiour rancke? no, Divine juſtice required that they who were drawn into the ſame fault, ſhould be enwrapped in the ſame condemnation: when there were but two in all the world to tranſgreſſe, concerning that onely forbidden fruit, the example of the one inticed the other, but did that extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the fault? Nothing leſſe: if any man therefore through ignorance hath beene drawne to the practiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f this ſinne? (and I perſwade my ſelfe did ſome know how dangerous a practiſe Vſury is, they would never venter their ſoules upon it) let ſuch as they tender their owne ſoules, take notice how this of ignorance will not excuſe, but rather condemne them that have ſo good meanes of better reſolution, if God would move their hearts to ſeeke after it: be well reſolved then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your practiſe, truſt not your owne reſolution in this caſe; <hi>Mammon</hi> is ſubtle to beguile you, therefore be as diligent to take counſell for your ſoules in Religion, as you are for your bodies in Phyſicke, or your goods in law; and deſire no leſſe ſecurity of conſcience in this queſtion of Vſury, than you doe for your principall in the practice of it: Let not the practiſe of ſome one miniſter amongſt you encourage any to the like practiſe, or becauſe it is a queſtion, therefore becauſe it is a queſtion, let it not arme any againſt remorſe or touch of conſcience. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. Fent. </seg>
               </label> Thoſe that have written moſt favourably of it, reverend Maſter <hi>Calvin,</hi> who is the ſuppoſed Patron of Vſury, doth no way countenance it, as it is practiſed in theſe dayes: If any man therefore ſhall take you aſide, as <hi>Peter</hi> did <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.23.</note> to favour your dealing herein, ſuſpect that whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering to ſavour not the things which bee of God, but the things that be of men.</p>
            <p>From example, let us come in the ſecond place to affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is as perverſe in judgement, as the former is po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull, to lead into errour; this ſeemes to ariſe out of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but Charity is no Charity if it oppoſe Iuſtice: 'tis a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell pitty that tenders the outward eſtate of any to the hurt and prejudice of the ſoule. If Vſury (ſay ſome) be not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any to practiſe: Alas! What ſhall become of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9966:11"/>poore Orphants and Widowes, in theſe unjuſt dayes, that have Stockes of Money left them, and want skill to imploy the ſame? By Gods helpe they ſhall doe well: Our greater care ſhould be, what ſhall become of poore Orphans and Widowes, in theſe uncharitable dayes, that have no Stockes at all left them: though (I confeſſe) both the one and the other are alike in this, that they are not ſo able to helpe themſelves as others be; therefore there be no two eſtates among men, over whom God hath a more provident and tender care, than over Widowes and fatherleſſe children;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> 22.</note> he hath provided for them by a ſpeciall Law, Thou ſhalt not trouble any Widow or fatherleſſe child: No one Law more iterated by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and frequently urged by the Prophets, than this, for the ſafegard of Orphants and Widowes: Whom, if mortall men ſhall neglect, God himſelfe (in his fatherly providence) will be their protector:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. <hi>v.</hi> 5.</note> He is a Father of the fatherleſſe, and a Iudge of the Widow; even God in his holy habitation (as the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes.) Yea, God would worke a Miracle, rather than the poore Widow of the ſonne of the Prophets, with her two fatherleſſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Kings</hi> 4.1.</note> ſhould want. The Sonne of God ſhewes the like ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affection, in denouncing a Woe againſt ſuch as devoured Widowes houſes: And his Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> meaſures true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.14. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.</note> and undefiled before God, even the Father, by charitie towards the fatherleſſe and Widowes. Hath God then ſo many wayes bound himſelfe by promiſe to provide for Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and Orphants; and ſhall theſe, by Vſurie, withdraw themſelves out of his fatherly providence? Shall theſe be ſecured by Vſurious Contracts, againſt the Act of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? Certainely, God will take it more unkindly at their hands than at any other. Obſerve but the difference in this point, betwixt the wiſdome of God and the World: The World thinkes Vſurie the beſt and ſafeſt way for Orphants and Widowes, becauſe it doth ſecure them moſt from all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualties which may fall vpon their eſtates by any act, eyther of God or man: the wiſdome of God contrariwiſe is, That theſe perſons ſhould moſt of all caſt their care upon him,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9966:12"/>becauſe he cares moſt for them. But of all practiſes, Vſurie doth moſt withdraw them from dependance upon Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly providence; which beſt beſeemes their condition. If Vſurie then be unlawfull in caſe of Orphants, 'tis moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull: And doubtleſſe, if Almightie God had thought it fit to have tolerated Vſurie in theſe perſons, he might as eaſily have mentioned the ſame,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19.</note> as hee doth the toleration of len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſtrangers. But it was ſo farre from his meaning, that in the very ſame place where hee makes a Law for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Orphants and Widowes, preſently upon it is annexed the Law againſt Vſurie.<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>22.22.</hi> &amp;c.</note> Shall theſe then, who are ſo well provided for by a ſpeciall Law of God, be tranſgreſſors of the very next Law unto it? God forbid! Orphants are comming into the World, Widowes (who intend to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſo) are going out of the World. And ſhall theſe two Ages (which of all other ought to be moſt heavenly, the one for innocencie, the other for devotion) be ſtayned with Vſurie? Chriſt is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> unto us, the firſt and the laſt, the beginning and the end: And ſhall the <hi>Alpha</hi> of our Nonage, and the <hi>Omega</hi> of our Dotage, be dedicated to Vſurie? Chriſt calls himſelfe by the name of a Letter, the firſt Letter in the Alphabet, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. Fent. de Vſur. </seg>
               </label> that children may learne Chriſt ſo ſoone as they are able to know their Letters: And ſhall we ſuffer our children to be dyed in the Wooll of their infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie with that ſcarlet ſinne of Vſurie?</p>
            <p>And as for Widowes that profeſſe themſelves now in their latter age, to leave the World, to betake themſelves to God, to be ſo married unto their onely Husband, Chriſt, as that they may quietly ſay their Prayers, heare Sermons, and live upon Vſurie: Alas! Who ever taught them thus to joyne God and <hi>Mammon</hi> together? Let ſuch looke into their owne eſtate and condition: God hath made them Stewards of their owne Stocke of Money; 'tis they that ſtand anſwerable before God, for the uſe or abuſe of ſuch Summes put forth into the hands of others: and when they gaine eight in the Hundred, the Borrowers muſt gaine a great deale more cleare, beſides many Charges and Duties
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9966:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be payd out of their Gaine: And how doe theſe Widowes know who is oppreſt or bitten by this Gaine? Let ſuch then be troubled in Conſcience for this ſinne;<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>Mordeat hic ut moriatur illic:</hi> Let the Worme bite here, that it may dye elſewhere.</p>
            <p>As for old men, who decaying in the faculties of minde and body, are forced to leave their Trade; and then they aske what they ſhall doe, having gotten ſome Money to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a lawfull Calling, and are not able to follow it any longer? For my part, I can tell them what they muſt not doe. Is there no Fruit in the Garden, but the forbidden Fruit? Have they ſpent their ſtrength, and worne their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to live at eaſe (without labour) when they are old; and have they not taken ſome care for the eaſe of conſcience, how to live without ſinne, when they are aged? Will they intangle their ſoules in the practice of Vſurie, when they have one foot in the grave? Hath God bleſſed their labours in youth, and will they forſake him in age? What a ſhame is it, that they ſhould pollute themſelves with filthy Lucre, when they ſhould be moſt dedicated to Devotion? The unjuſt Steward when hee was to give over his Stewardſhip,<note place="margin">Luke <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> (and ſo muſt old men ſhortly doe) hee conſults with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe what to doe; <hi>Fodere neſcio mendicare erubeſco;</hi> take paines hee cannot, thoſe dayes are paſt; ſpend upon the Principall, would ſoone bring him to beggerie: at laſt hee concludes; I know what I will doe, I will turne a hundred into a hundred and eight. I commend theſe men, as our Saviour did the unjuſt Steward, for doing wiſely: wiſe, in that they make choyſe of ſo eaſie, ſo ſecure a gaine: (For <hi>Plinie</hi> calls Vſurie, <hi>Quaeſtuoſa ſegnitius;</hi> and another as wittily, <hi>Chimiani Satanae,</hi> the Devils Alchimie) I ſay ſo great and certaine gaine, fit for ſuch Seniors: for they are <hi>attentiores ad rem, quo minus viae eò plus viatici;</hi> moſt ſtudious of proviſion in age, when the way is ſhorteſt. The children of this World (ſayth our Saviour in the ſame Chapter) are wiſer in their generations than the children of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9966:13"/>Light; wiſer than the Patriarkes and Prophets of the Old Teſtament; wiſer than the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts of the New; wiſer than the Fathers and Councels of ſucceeding ages; wiſer than any of the Saints of God that lived in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times; for wee read of none of them that had the wit either to practiſe Vſury themſelves, or by any diſtinction to approve of it, finde it lawfull in others: nay, the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with their moſt acute and ſubtle wits, who did ſet themſelves to coyne diſtinctions, and to finde out the moſt exact difference of things, that were able to dart an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the men of <hi>Gibeon</hi> did ſtones at a haires breadth;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 20.16.</note> yet were never ſo quicke-ſighted as ſome in theſe dayes are, to finde out a diſtinction to ſalve a Vſurers conſcience.</p>
            <p>Others againe, urge a ſuppoſed neceſſity of Vſury, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that the ſtate of a Corporation cannot ſtand, traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke cannot be maintained, Tradeſ-men cannot live without it; I confeſſe my ignorance in matters of pollicy, but I am ſure that rule of the Apoſtle holds true in Divinity,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> We muſt not doe evill that good may come thereof. Beſides, I would aske theſe men, that pretend they cannot live without taking up mony at intereſt; is their meaning that they cannot live in that pompe they doe, maintaine their wives in thoſe faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that they doe, drive their Trades to that height which they doe? if this be all, the anſwer is eaſie? perhaps God would not have them beare ſo great a ſayle as they doe, but to drinke of the waters of their owne Well,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.15.</note> to be content with ſuch bleſſings as Gods fatherly providence doth offer them; there is no neceſſity for a man to enrich himſelfe by ſuch practiſes as are forbidden, or unlawfull: Better is a little with the feare of the Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.16.</note> than great treaſure with trouble. Gods Law did ever intend that men ſhould lend one another in charity, to the poore in friendſhip, to their equalls to receive the like courteſie againe; which duty, if men would but practice, there were no neceſſity of Vſury. A Drunkard hath brought his body to ſuch a habit, that unleſſe he drinke liberally, even to the turning of his braines,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9966:13"/>he will be ſicke againe; is not drunkenneſſe in that man ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, becauſe ſo neceſſary? A proud woman hath beene wedded ſo long to her will, that if ſhee be croſſed in it, ſhee will grow mad for pride, like <hi>Nabuchadnezzar,</hi> or elſe dye with fretfulneſſe (like a Weezill in a Cage) ſhall her wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe be excuſed, becauſe her devilliſh ſtomacke is growne too ſtrong for her wit? So then you may take notice of the weakneſſe of this argument, that Vſury muſt therefore needs be lawfull, becauſe ſome mens ambition or covetouſneſſe hath made it neceſſary. And here may be touched that que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion moved by <hi>Aquinas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2.2.73. <hi>queſt. art.</hi> 4.</note> whether a man may lawfully borrow mony upon Vſury? for the Apoſtle ſaith; that they are worthy of death, not onely they that doe the ſame,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.31.</note> but they that favour them that doe them. 'Tis anſwered that no man ought to induce another to ſinne, yet a man may make uſe of another mans ſinne to ſome good end, ſo God oftentimes makes uſe of ſome mens wickednes to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes; ſo a man may lawfully give Vſury where inevitable occaſions ſhall inforce an invincible neceſſity, eyther for the preſervation of his credit and eſtate, or for ſupply of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent wants, eyther of nature or perſon, as it is lawfull for a man (falling amongſt Theeves) to tell how much money hee hath, to the end, hee may have his life: According to the example of thoſe tenne men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 41.8.</note> who ſaid to <hi>Iſmael, Slay us not, for wee have Treaſure in the Field.</hi> If theſe occaſions bee impoſed and not drawne upon a man by ſome former negligence or default, if he attempt to borrow no more than hee ſhall be able to pay at the time, if upon ſuch occaſions he cannot borrow free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then is he no agent in the ſinne, but a meere patient in the opreſſion of Vſury.</p>
            <p>To conclude then, let not thoſe poore evaſions of biting and toothleſſe Vſury deceive us, they are but as figge leaves, ſhapen by ſome indulgent wits to cover the nakedneſſe of that which the Law of God, of nature, and equity have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to be deformed and naked in it ſelfe, as if there were
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9966:14"/>ſome Vſury without the meaning of Gods Law, or as if God had never meant to condemne Vſurers, but onely to muzzle them for biting: ſome are content to moderate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this kinde of gaine, and then if it be a ſinne, 'tis but a little one (as <hi>Lot</hi> ſaid of <hi>Zoar</hi>) and my ſoule ſhall live;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.20.</note> 
               <hi>Modicae ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> quae perdunt nos,</hi> they are little ones that und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e us; a meat in the eye, if it bee not gotten forth in time, may grow to a pinne and a webbe: And a mans conſcience may ſuffer ſhippe-wracke as well on a ſand as upon a rocke; he that heapes up moderate ſinnes wrackes his ſoule upon a ſand, and ſo ſinking by little and little, his conſcience is at length ſwallowed without any ſenſe or fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at all.</p>
            <p>And as for that perſonall exception, let not that deceive us, becauſe ſome will not oppreſſe the poore; therefore they will lend their money to a rich Merchant. Doth the Aſſe bray,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 6.5.</note> when hee hath Provender; or loweth the Oxe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, when hee hath Fodder? To what end doth bee borrow, being of ſufficient wealth already? but onely that hee may compaſſe greater matters than his owne ſtocke will reach unto; what warrant is there in equity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, either for him to borrow, or ſuch to lend? let him plow with his owne Heifer, and drinke of the Waters of his owne Well;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.</note> let him follow the Apoſtles rule, to be content with what hee hath: If this were practiſed, then would not the greater Merchants, like the great Fiſhes, ſwallow the leſſer Frie, but all might live comfortably one by another.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let Charitie, Iuſtice, Pietie, Nature her ſelfe, the Lawes of God and man, all authoritie ancient and moderne, (joyning their forces againſt this ſinne) at laſt prevaile againſt it. For my owne part, I have endevoured to ſatisfie my ſelfe in this point; for I had rather finde my ſelfe at home in my owne conſcience, than ſeeke my ſelfe abroad, in other mens practiſes.<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.</note> And in the next place, I have preſumed a little to trouble Iſrael in this ſinne: I know I ſhall incurre varietie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9966:14"/>of cenſure; ſo that being thought too buſie, perhaps I ſhall be conſtrained to take up that Text of Scripture,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.6.</note> * <hi>Loe thus am I wounded in the houſe of my friends.</hi> But be they friends, or be they ſtrangers; let them ſtrike with their tongue, and wound at their pleaſure; if I haue awakened but any one mans conſcience, to ſee the wounds that this ſinne hath made in it, I have my reward. Let me crave your attention to one obſervation upon the Text, and ſo I will conclude: <hi>Thou oughteſt to have given my money to the Exchangers, &amp;c. that when I had come, I might have had my owne</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with advantage, 'tis in ſome Tranſlations; the Vulgar, <hi>cum Vſura; Beza, cum foenore:</hi> the word is properly, with Vſurie. Here we ſee God is the Vſurer, len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Talents unto men to lay out, that he may have his owne againe with intereſt. <hi>Qui prohibet te eſſe foeneratorem ille jubet te eſſe foeneratorem</hi> (ſayth Saint <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Pſal. <hi>36.</hi> Serm. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>) Hee that forbids thee to be an Vſurer, commands thee to be an Vſurer, <hi>(viz.)</hi> in the diſpenſation of thoſe ſpirituall gifts which God beſtowes upon us.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.25.</note> * In the Tabernacle there were ſmall and great Veſſels; ſome ſmaller Cups, ſome greater Goblets: yet all theſe Veſſels, both ſmall and great, did ſerve for the uſe of the Tabernacle. So ſhould it be in the Church: euery one ſhould imploy the Talent which hee hath received, to the beſt advantage that he can; to the glory of God, and the ſalvation of his owne ſoule. <hi>Nolite qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcere lucrari Chriſto quia lucrati eſtis à Chriſto</hi> (ſayth Saint <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>) Let us not ceaſe to bee gayners unto Chriſt, becauſe wee our ſelves were gayned by him. The Miniſters muſt give their Money to the Exchangers, <hi>(i.)</hi> they muſt preach the Word of God unto the people, (ſo venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Bede</hi> upon <hi>Luke</hi> 19.) <hi>Qui verbi pecuniam à Doctore percipit emitque credendo neceſse eſt eam cum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuris ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat operando, ut quod auditu didicit exequatur &amp; actu;</hi> Hee that hath received that heavenly Money of Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Word from the mouth of the Preacher, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay it againe with intereſt, <hi>(i.)</hi> Hee muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:9966:15"/>hath heard with his eare, to expreſſe in his life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; labouring to ſay with Saint <hi>Paul:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10.</note> 
               <hi>The grace that was in me, was not in vaine.</hi> Where God ſoweth, hee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects his Harveſt: and no Graine ſo meane in our eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, out of which in proportion hee expects not a timely Croppe.</p>
            <p>This is that ſpirituall Vſurie which God requires at our hands: Which if wee ſtrive to pay him here, wee ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, both Paſtor and people, heare that happie Welcome which our Saviour himſelfe pronounceth to thoſe two faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Servants in the 23. Verſe of this Chapter, <hi>Enter into the joy of your Maſter.</hi> Into which joy, thou O Father, bring us all, for thy deare Sonnes ſake, Chriſt Ieſus: to whom, with thy ſelfe and bleſſed Spirit, be aſcribed all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
